Chapter 14. Nantucket.
Nothing more happened on the passage worthy of mentioning. So after a fine
run, we safely arrived in Nantucket.
Nantucket. Take out your map and look at it. See what a real corner of the world
it occupies. How it stands there away offshore, more lonely than the Eddie
Stone Lighthouse. Look at it. A mere hillock and elbow of sand, all beach and
without a background. There is more sand there than you would use in 20 years as
a substitute for blotting paper. Some gamesome whites will tell you that they
have to plant weeds there, that they don't grow naturally, that they import
Canada thistles, that they have to send beyond seas for a spile to stop a leak
in an oil cask, that pieces of wood in Nantucket are carried about like bits of
the true cross in Rome, that people there plant toad stools before their
house to get under the shade in summertime. That one blade of grass
makes an oasis, three blades in a day's walk a prairie. That they wear quicksand
shoes, something like laplander snowshoes. That they are so shut up,
belted about every way enclosed, surrounded, and made an utter island of
by the ocean, that to their very chairs and tables small clams will sometimes be
found adhering as to the backs of sea turtles.
But these extravaganzas only show that Nantucket is no Illinois.
Look now at the wondrous traditional story of how this island was settled by
the Red Men. Thus goes the legend. In olden times an eagle swooped down upon
the New England coast and carried off an infant Indian in its talons. With loud
laments the parents saw their child born out of sight over the wide waters. They
resolved to follow in the same direction. Setting out in their canoes
after a perilous passage they discovered the island, and there they found an
empty ivory casket, the poor little Indians skeleton.
What wonder then, that these Nantucketers, born on a beach, should
take to the sea for a livelihood. They first caught crabs and quhogs in the
sand. Grown boulder, they waited out with nets for mackerel. More experience
they pushed off in boats and captured Cod, and at last launching a navy of
great ships on the sea, explored this watery world, put an incessant belt of
circumnavigations round it, peeped in at bearing straits, and in all seasons and
all oceans declared everlasting war with the mightiest animated mass that has
survived the flood, most monstrous and most mountainous, that Himalayan salt
seam mastadon, clothed with such portentiousness, of unconscious power
that his very panics are more to be dreaded than his most fearless and
malicious assaults. And thus of these naked Nantucketers, these sea hermits,
issuing from their antill in the sea, overrun and conquered the watery world
like so many Alexanders, parceling out among them the Atlantic, Pacific, and
Indian oceans, as the three pirate powers did Poland. Let America add
Mexico to Texas and pile Cuba upon Canada. Let the English overswarm all
India and hang out their blazing banner from the sun. Twothirds of this
terraquous globe are the Nantucketers.
For the sea is his. He owns it as emperor's own empires. Other seaman
having but a right of way through it.
Merchant ships are but extension bridges, armed ones but floating forts.
Even pirates and privateeers, though following the sea as highwaymen the
road, they but plunder other ships, other fragments of the land like
themselves, without seeking to draw their living from the bottomless deep
itself. The Nantucketer, he alone resides and riots on the sea. He alone,
in Bible language, goes down to it in ships, to and fro, plowing it as his own
special plantation. There is his home.
There lies his business which a Noah's flood would not interrupt, though it
overwhelmed all the millions in China.
He lives on the sea as prairie in the prairie. He hides among the waves.
He climbs them as shamwa hunters climb the Alps. For years he knows not the
land, so that when he comes to it at last it smells like another world, more
strangely than the moon would to an earthman. with the landless gull that at
sunset folds her wings and is rocked to sleep between billows. So at nightfall
the nantucketer out of sight of land furls his sails and lays him to his rest
while under his very pillow rush herds of walruses and whales.